Hey, gang.
여러분
Look, I know what you're thinking.
무슨 생각하는지 알아요
This week was supposed to be training week.
이번 주는 훈련 주간이었어야 해요
I set it all up to be all about fine tuning frontier models.
개척 시대 모델들을 세심하게 조정하는 일을 시작했죠
And what haven't we done?
우리가 안 한 게 뭐죠?
We haven't fine tuned frontier models.
개척 시대 모델은 잘 몰라요
But I have good news.
좋은 소식이 있어요
Today is the day.
오늘이 그날이에요
But I should prepare you that today may also disappoint in some ways as well as we will.
하지만 오늘 우리가 실망할 수도 있다는 걸 미리 알려드리죠
We will find out.
곧 알게 되겠죠
Um, but be prepared for that as we embark upon a whole brave new world, we're getting finally to training.
하지만 그걸 각오해야 해요 완전히 새로운 세상에 나가 드디어 훈련을 시작하니까요
And as a quick recap, you can already generate text and code with frontier models, with APIs and using
간단히 요약하자면 프런티어 모델과 API로 텍스트와 코드를 생성할 수 있고
open source models hugging face through both the pipelines and the the lower level transformers APIs.
파이프라인과 하위 레벨 트랜스포머 API를 서로 끌어안는 오픈 소스 모델을 사용할 수 있죠
Like using the models directly, you can create advanced Rag pipelines using Lange chain and not using
모델을 직접 사용하는 것처럼 랭 체인이 아닌 래그 파이프라인을 만들 수 있어요
And most importantly, you can now follow a five step strategy for problem solving that includes a lot
가장 중요한 건 큐레이팅에 많은 시간을 들이는 문제 해결을 위한 5단계 전략을
of time we seem to spend curating data.
따를 수 있다는 거죠
It turns out that lots of time is spent curating data and then making a baseline model.
많은 시간을 데이터를 큐레이팅하고 기준 모델을 만드는 데 할애하죠
We did some training, but it was training of a baseline model.
훈련을 좀 했지만 기본 모델 훈련이었어요
Traditional ML or we've not yet done is trained, fine tuned, a frontier model.
전통적인 ML은 아직 완성되지 않았어요 미세하게 훈련된 개척지 모델이죠
And that's what we're going to do today.
오늘 그걸 할 거예요
Going to understand the process for fine tuning in front of your model, create a data set for it,
모델 앞에서 미세 튜닝 과정을 이해하고 데이터 세트를 생성하고 미세
run fine tuning, and then test our new fine tuned model.
튜닝을 실행한 후 새 미세 튜닝 모델을 테스트하는 거죠
And just as a point of order to explain when you're talking about training, when in the context of
훈련에 대해 설명하자면 이런 모델에서 세밀한 조정은
these kinds of models, fine tuning is synonymous with with training, we never, of course, train
훈련과 동의어입니다 물론 처음부터 훈련하진 않습니다
one of these things from scratch, because that would cost north of hundreds of millions of dollars.
그러면 수억 달러가 들 테니까요
So we're always taking an existing model that's been trained, a pre-trained model, and we are doing
우리는 항상 훈련된 기존 모델을 사용합니다 미리 훈련된 모델이죠 전송 학습을
more training, taking advantage of transfer learning, which is this theory that says that you can
활용해 더 많은 훈련을 합니다 이 이론은 기존에 훈련된
just take an existing pre-trained model, do a bit more training, and it will be better at the new
모델을 가지고 더 많은 훈련을 하면 새 작업에서 더 낫다는
task you're training it for.
거죠
And that's also known as fine tuning.
그걸 미세 조정이라고 하죠
So with that vocabulary out of the way, let's just talk about the three steps to fine tuning with OpenAI.
이제 어휘력 문제를 해결했으니 오픈AI를 조정하는 세 가지 단계에 대해 이야기해 보죠
There's three things we need to follow in order to take GPT four zero or GPT four mini that we will
GPT 40과 4 미니를 받아들이려면 세 가지를 따라야 합니다 이 세
take and fine tune it.
가지를 잘 조율해야 하죠
The first step is you need to prepare training data that it will use for training.
첫 단계는 훈련에 사용할 훈련 데이터를 준비하는 거예요
We obviously use training data in the context of the traditional models, linear regression and so on.
전통적인 모델의 맥락에서 훈련 데이터를 사용합니다 선형 회귀 같은 거죠
We got some training examples and we pumped it through a linear regression model.
훈련용 견본을 구해서 선형 회귀 모델로 주입했어요
So we have to create training data.
훈련 데이터를 만들어야 해요
Now um, and then we have to upload it to OpenAI.
이제 오픈AI에 업로드 해야 해요
And it expects that training data in a particular format called JSON L which stands for JSON lines,
JSON L이라는 특정한 포맷의 훈련 데이터를 기대합니다 JSON 라인을 약자로 하죠
which is subtly different as I will show you to normal JSON.
미묘하게 달라요 일반적인 JSON을 보여드리죠
We are then going to run our training, our fine tuning and these charts all pointing downwards.
그다음 훈련과 미세한 조율을 실시할 겁니다 이 도표들은 모두 아래를 가리키죠
Might might trouble you.
당신이 곤란해질지도 몰라요
It looks like things are going wrong, but au contraire, when it comes to training, your one is watching.
뭔가 잘못되고 있는 것처럼 보이지만 그 반대입니다 훈련할 때 여러분의 상대는 지켜보고 있죠
Training loss.
훈련의 손실이죠
And of course you want loss to go down.
물론 손실이 줄어들길 바라죠
That means that things are getting better.
상황이 나아지고 있다는 뜻이죠
And so we will be watching our charts like a hawk and trying to make sure that our losses are coming
그래서 매의 눈으로 도표를 보면서 손실이 줄어드는지 확인할
down.
거예요
Uh, and most importantly, you look at training loss during the course of a batch, and you also look
가장 중요한 것은 한 배치에서 트레이닝 손실과 유효성 검증 손실입니다.
at validation loss, which is on a held out data set.
데이터 집합에 있는 것이죠.
Uh, is that coming down, too?
저것도 내려가요?
Because you may be overfitting to your training data if you just watch training loss.
훈련 데이터에 과부하가 걸릴 수 있으니까요
And that actually isn't a problem in our case, because we're only going to be running one epoch through
사실 우리 경우엔 그게 문제가 아닙니다 트레이닝 데이터로 한 개의 epoch만 실행할
our training data.
테니까요
And epoch is what you call it.
이포크라고도 하죠
When you go, you take take a complete training run all the way through your training data, and then
훈련 데이터를 통해 완전한 훈련을 한 다음 같은 데이터를
you repeat and do it all a second time with the same data.
반복해서 실행하는 거죠
That would be called a second epoch of training.
그런 걸 두 번째 수련 시대라고 하죠
And we are not going to do that because we have so much training data that we don't need to do that.
하지만 그렇게 하지 않을 겁니다 훈련 데이터가 너무 많아서 그럴 필요가 없으니까요
We might as well just use a bit more training data and do one epoch.
트레이닝 데이터를 더 활용해 하나의 시대를 만드는 게 낫겠어요 비트 코스트
And since all of the data will always be new data, the training loss is just as useful for us as validation
모든 데이터는 항상 새로운 데이터이기 때문에 훈련의 손실은 검증의 손실만큼이나
loss.
유용하죠
And then finally you evaluate your results.
그리고 마지막으로 결과를 평가하죠
And then based on what you see, you tweak and you repeat and keep going.
그걸 바탕으로 수정하고 반복해서 계속하는 거죠
So those are the stages.
그게 무대예요
And as I say, the first of them is to prepare the data.
말씀드렸듯이 첫 번째는 데이터를 준비하는 거죠
So OpenAI expects it in this format called JSON L, which means that it is a series of lines of JSON
OpenAI는 JSON L이라는 포맷에서 그걸 기대합니다 JSON 데이터의 일련의 라인이라는
data.
뜻이죠
And you may think, isn't that just the same as JSON data?
JSON 데이터와 똑같다고 생각하실지도 몰라요
It's not.
아니에요
It's not in a in a collection.
컬렉션에 있는 게 아니에요
So it's not in a list.
목록에 없군요
It doesn't start with a square bracket with with commas.
쉼표가 붙은 대괄호로 시작하진 않아요
It's just each row, each line in this file is a separate JSON object starting and ending with curly
이 파일의 각 행, 각 줄은 중괄호로 시작하고 끝나는 별개의 JSON 객체예요
It's a subtle distinction, but it can catch you out if you're not expecting that you're not writing
미묘한 차이점이지만 JSON 개체를 작성하지 않을 거라는 기대는 안 할 경우에
a JSON object, because that would have a list around it.
걸릴 수 있어요 주변에 리스트가 있을 테니까요
You're writing rows of JSON to this file, and then each row is going to be something that is mostly
이 파일에 JSON 행을 작성하는 거죠 그럼 각각의 행은 우리에게 아주 익숙한
very familiar to us.
것이 돼요
It will have one attribute called messages.
메시지라는 하나의 특성을 갖게 되죠
And what goes in there is the thing that we know so well, the list of dictionaries where each dictionary
그 안에는 우리가 잘 아는 것이 들어있습니다 각 사전마다 역할과 내용이 있는
has a role and a content.
사전 목록이죠
It's a conversation.
대화예요
So that is what is going in each row.
각 행에 들어가는 거죠
As you will see, we will craft this particular type of data set for uploading.
보다시피 업로드를 위한 이 특정 유형의 데이터 세트를 만들 거예요
All right.
좋아요
With that enough enough chit chat.
잡담은 이 정도면 충분해요
Let's go to Jupyter Lab.
주피터 연구소로 가요
Let's actually run this thing.
실제로 실행해보죠
And for the first time we will train a frontier model.
그리고 처음으로 개척지 모델을 훈련할 거예요
Let's do it.
시작하죠